<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>hardware on Zeroth Oughts</title><link>https://vjarnot.github.io/tags/hardware/</link><description>Recent content in hardware on Zeroth Oughts</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vjarnot.github.io/tags/hardware/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Kingston NV2 (HP Z Turbo G2 M.2 PCIe Adapter) vs onboard NVME</title><link>https://vjarnot.github.io/posts/2023-02-28-hpnvme-vs-onboard/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vjarnot.github.io/posts/2023-02-28-hpnvme-vs-onboard/</guid><description>Tested two fast drives and a slow drive. CrystalDiskMark numbers which aren&amp;#39;t good benchmarks, but they&amp;#39;ll be funny to re-read in 10-20 years.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Disclaimer: These are not real benchmarks, these are some adhoc numbers for my personal amusement. These are the result of 1 run per drive on my machine, there was no attempt
to do multiple runs or otherwise control for any variables.</em></p>
<h2 id="sk-hynix-p41-asus-z790-cpu-nvme">SK Hynix P41 (ASUS Z790 CPU NVME)</h2>
<p>This is considered the current top dog in the consumer NVME space. I&rsquo;m certain that PCIe 5 versions will outperform it relatively soon, but it&rsquo;s plenty fast at the start of 2023.
SK Hynix advertises 7,000 MB/s sequential read and 6,500 MB/s sequential write; 1,200 TBW durability-wise.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/posts/2023-02-28-hpnvme-vs-onboard/2023-02-28-160531-crystaldiskmark-skhynixp41.png" type="" alt="P41"  /></p>
<h2 id="wd-sn850x-asus-z790-chipset-nvme">WD SN850X (ASUS Z790 Chipset NVME)</h2>
<p>This is the just-as-good or almost-as-good contender to the P41, depending on who you read. Western Digital advertises 7,300 MB/s sequential read and 6,350 MB/s sequential write.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/posts/2023-02-28-hpnvme-vs-onboard/2023-02-28-161106-crystaldiskmark-wdsn850x.png" type="" alt="SN850X"  /></p>
<h2 id="kinston-nv2-hp-z-turbo-g2-m2-pcie-adapter">Kinston NV2 (HP Z Turbo G2 M.2 PCIe Adapter)</h2>
<p>One can compare the above two NVME cards, whereas this one is in a different class. I intentionally went bargain hunting, since the <a href="https://vjarnot.github.io/posts/2023-02-27-hp-zturbog2-modding/">HP PCIe NVME adapter</a>
 is going into a decade-old
PC which only has a PCIe 2.0 slot available, so speeds will be limited by that interface rather than the NVME drive itself. Kingston advertises 3,500 MB/s sequential read speed. You can see
that this drive does indeed have less raw throughput than those above, but - for random-access workloads - it&rsquo;s really keeping up quite well.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/posts/2023-02-28-hpnvme-vs-onboard/2023-02-28-155913-crystaldiskmark-hpnvmekingston.png" type="" alt="NV2"  /></p>
<hr>
<h4 id="amazon-links-in-case-youre-here-shopping-for-some-reason">Amazon links in case you&rsquo;re here shopping for some reason:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/3ZaxG06" target="_blank" rel="noopener">SK Hynix P41</a>
</li>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/3ZpAret" target="_blank" rel="noopener">WD SN850X</a>
</li>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/3Z9CPWq" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kingston NV2</a>
</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Modding the HP Z Turbo G2 M.2 PCIe Adapter</title><link>https://vjarnot.github.io/posts/2023-02-27-hp-zturbog2-modding/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vjarnot.github.io/posts/2023-02-27-hp-zturbog2-modding/</guid><description>This HP card mounts in a PCIe expansion slot and provides a M.2 NVME socket. But then it gets weird - HP locked these so they could only be used with HP Z4x0s. Or did they?</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="modding-the-hp-z-turbo-g2-m2-pcie-adapter">Modding the HP Z Turbo G2 M.2 PCIe Adapter</h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/posts/2023-02-27-hp-zturbog2-modding/hp-card-finished.jpg" type="" alt="The End Result"  /></p>
<h3 id="why-though">Why, though?</h3>
<p>PCIe cards which take a NVME &lsquo;drive&rsquo; - allowing you to add NVME storage even if you&rsquo;re out of M.2 slots (or never had any) - aren&rsquo;t rare or expensive.
They tend to run in the $50 range. The HP card in question here is about a decade old and can be had for about $12 on eBay. However, <strong>however</strong>, <em><strong>HOWEVER</strong></em>: HP -
in their infinite idiocy - actually spent money and time making sure this particular card wouldn&rsquo;t work outside of a HP Z4xx workstation.</p>
<p>I <em>intentionally</em> purchased one of these locked cards on eBay - not for the savings - they&rsquo;re not significant enough to take a gamble on used hardware. No, <strong>I bought this
card specifically due to this forum post:</strong> <a href="https://forums.servethehome.com/index.php?threads/need-help-with-hp-z-turbo-drive-g2-512gb.21195/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://forums.servethehome.com/index.php?threads/need-help-with-hp-z-turbo-drive-g2-512gb.21195/</a>
</p>
<p>This, folks, is what made/makes the internet wonderful: a ludicrously niche and esoteric problem posted on a forum, with an absolutely mind-boggling solution posted almost immediately thereafter.</p>
<p>Allow me to quote obrith from the link above:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We ordered a batch of Z420&rsquo;s in with these cards and some users didn&rsquo;t want the PCIe slot taken up so we ended up with pulls we wanted to use elsewhere.
You have to remove the Q1 transistor. The card just constantly resets unless the computer sends a command to stop resetting (only the listed HP models will do that)
unless you physically disable the &lsquo;feature&rsquo;.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Seriously though, <a href="https://forums.servethehome.com/index.php?threads/need-help-with-hp-z-turbo-drive-g2-512gb.21195/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">read the thread</a>
, it really <em>is</em> what makes the internet great.</p>
<p>So, why? That&rsquo;s why - to actively enjoy and support this type of information exchange and hardware hacking.</p>
<h3 id="so-whats-the-modification">So, what&rsquo;s the modification?</h3>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/posts/2023-02-27-hp-zturbog2-modding/Inkedhp-card-before_LI.jpg" type="" alt="HP NVME Card Before"  /></p>
<p>That circled component has to go. I don&rsquo;t have pictures of the process because a) I only have two hands and b) nobody should have to watch me wield a soldering iron.
That said, the process is relatively simple - heat up the connections (3 in this case) with the soldering iron tip, and simultaneously pull on the component (tweezers come in handy).</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/posts/2023-02-27-hp-zturbog2-modding/Inkedhp-card-after_LI.jpg" type="" alt="HP NVME Card After"  /></p>
<h3 id="results-results">Results? Results!</h3>
<p>It works! This part is very boring - the card does what it is supposed to do. I bought this card to go into a computer that only has a PCIe 2.0 x4 slot available, so I bought a
very cheap NVME drive for it, because I won&rsquo;t end up getting full NVME speeds from PCIe 2.0 anyway, therefore the drive doesn&rsquo;t need to be particularly fast. Fast for an NVME, that is, this
thing is still hugely faster than SATA SSDs. So this benchmark was less about speed, and more about whether it works or not:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/posts/2023-02-27-hp-zturbog2-modding/2023-02-28-155913-crystaldiskmark-hpnvmekingston.png" type="" alt="CrystalDiskMark Results"  /></p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>